I think the reason US for decades
for decades has weaponized the
occupation of Palestine has stood
steadfast behind the Zionist project is
because what the Palestinian movement
represents and is is Arab nationalism
the struggle to have control of your own
resources your own land and that's why
it's so crucial just like they did in
removing first nation peoples when this
country is being formed with the gen the
settler colonial genocide of around 12
million people is the people for the
project the colonial project to to um
succeed. You have to remove the people
from the land.
Hi, I'm John Kiryaku and welcome back to
Deep Focus.
Gaza remains in the news every single
day. And while we talk frequently about
human rights violations there and and
different things that the Israeli
military and government have done to
carry out what amounts to really a
genocide in Gaza, uh it still deserves
to be at the very top of our minds.
Well, we're recording this on Friday the
7th of November and uh I wanted I wanted
to tell you about a call I received
today. It was from a contact of mine in
the Israeli government. He said
something that was very interesting. He
said that the Israeli government has
reached out to private American
companies to redevelop Gaza. private
American companies working with the
Israeli government, not with Gaza
Palestinians,
to rebuild Gaza. I said to this contact
of mine, "What about the idea that the
Israeli press is talking about that
Israel would own Gaza, but Saudi Arabia
would administer it and would spend its
own oil money there to create a a port
and an airport and hospitals and pave
the roads and really get the place
going." and he said that's being
discussed in the newspapers but not by
members of the Israeli military.
So it looks like the fix is already in.
We're going to talk about this and other
issues related to Gaza with Seth
Donnelly. Seth is a longtime activist
and even more important than being an
activ activist, he's an author and the
co-founder of Taxpayers Against
Genocide. Seth S, thanks so much for for
joining us. I I'm I'm tongue tied here
because there's so much to say and so
little time to get it out. Thanks for
being with us today.
>> Really good to be here, John. Really
appreciate your program and your work.
>> Thank you. Appreciate everything that
that you're doing. And you know, the the
timing of this, Seth, is perfect because
>> this is American taxpayers money
transferred to the Israeli government
that is used to carry out this genocide
in in Gaza. Well, now it's time to start
rebuilding. Uh, and it looks like the
Israelis intend to lay ownership claim
to everything in Gaza. What did we make
of this?
>> Well, it it's um it's really what we're
seeing unfold, as you were saying in
your intro, is it's it's the ongoing
uh extension of the of the genocide. And
it's it's you know it's a it's really
the the genocide in the service of
ethnic cleansing and to um this sort of
violent gentrification that's going to
you know the Trump vision remember that
that ridiculous social media post he put
out of that video um can't remember if
it was 6 months or you know I think it
was about six months ago where it showed
gauze in the future and and he put it
out on his forum you know so it was it
was it was clearly absurd but yet Trump
put it out and we should therefore take
it seriously that it was showing Gaza in
the future without Palestinians and with
Trump and Netanyahu on the beach
together. Um but you know it's it's the
vision. We see a very similar thing
playing out in other parts of the world
too like for example in Haiti where
there's the slow motion genocide
happening uh under essentially a a de
facto occupation administered by the US
government and what's called the core
group ever since the coup against
president Ariststeed in 2004 and the
objective is to remove the people and
take over the the resources and so
clearly that's in play in Gaza and and
as you mentioned it's it's it's our tax
dollars that not only funded the bombs
but have also funded that are that are
funding this this this reconstruction
plan.
>> I've said uh I've said a number of times
that when I was stationed in Saudi
Arabia in 1991, long time ago now, 1991,
the the Saudis told us that they had
gone through a back channel to the
Israelis and said that they wanted to
develop Gaza. They wanted to build a a
seapport and an airport and a water
desalination plant and an electrical
grid. big ticket multi-billion dollar
items and the Israelis said absolutely
not. This is when Hamas was so tiny that
nobody was even paying attention to it.
And the Israelis said absolutely not.
There was never any plan to develop
Gaza. There was never any plan to allow
Gaza Palestinians to have, you know, 24
hours a day of electricity or 24 hours a
day of of portable water. Why why would
it be different now?
Exactly. I mean, what Trump Trump's
so-called peace plan is, as as many
people have been saying, particularly
Palestinian commentators, it's it's it's
neocolonial. It's a neoc colonial plan,
right? the the governance uh of of Gaza
will be turned over to what the media
euphemistically calls Palestinian
technocrats. But really uh the driving
force is the international
um board that uh Trump has named himself
and Tony Blair to to oversee. So it's
you know and then the US is coming in to
provide a command role with their with
military presence in Israel to
administer the the peace the
quoteunquote peacekeeping force. It's
supposed to roll out in phase two of the
ceasefire, which of course hasn't
happened yet. But, uh, in the meantime,
every day practically, people are being
killed. Um, Israel, per the plan,
committed to bring in 600 trucks of aid
per day. Um, they're only bringing in at
best a 100. So, they're only one six. It
was just about a week ago that in a
single day they killed over 100
Palestinians, about half of whom were
children. And um
you know it's it's it's an ongoing slow
at this point they've ratcheted down
from killing a 100 people a day to an
average maybe you know more like 10
people a day but the ongoing structures
of starvation and uh and deprivation
remain in effect. So it's to call this a
ceasefire is itself um somewhat
Orwellian.
Well, and you know, that's an
interesting thing because yeah, in here
in the West, we're calling it a
ceasefire. The the Israelis call it more
than a ceasefire. This is this is
Israel's opportunity to to, you know,
finally stomp out uh any remnants of uh
of resistance. I mentioned a minute ago
that today is Friday. We're recording
this on Friday, November 7th. This
morning, the government of Kazakhstan
announced that it was recognizing Israel
and opening an embassy as part of the
Abraham Accords. Nobody expected that.
Not that it really means terribly much.
Uh the real uh the real cherry on top of
the Abraham Accords for the Trump
administration and for the Israelis,
frankly, is going to be Saudi
recognition of Israel. What do countries
get Saudi Arabia aside? What do
countries get out of turning their backs
on the Palestinians and recognizing
Israel? What what is in Kazakhstan's
national interest that it would agree,
for example, to do something like this?
>> Well, I can't speak to the specifics of
Kazakhstan, but but certainly we see the
pressure that the Trump administration
is putting on central and East European
um countries. And there's I'm sure
there's a there's so a myriad of tactics
and pressure points and incentives. We
saw that when they were able to to peel
away like five or six additional
countries to be abstensions in the
recent vote against the blockade on Cuba
which were primarily central and east
European countries that um so there's
there are leverage what that exact
leverage points are in the case of
Kazakhstan I can't speak to but
certainly with Saudi Arabia you know I
just read that the crown prince is
coming to these states soon and it's a
way to further consolidate um well
consolidate is the wrong verb because
it's already fully consolidated over
decades that the petro dollar agreement
with Saudi Arabia and the weapons that
they get um from the US but it deepens
that relationship you know and clearly
the the Trump vision will be to have
joint venture foreign investment
partners including the Saudis in Gaza
which is uh resourcerich
um and um
and you know the it allows uh I just
read that Qatar had received a special
protection agreement from the United
States and it goes beyond even what the
Saudis have. So I think the Saudis are
still looking to to deepen their
relationship um the monarchy uh with the
US and of course they fear their own
population. The Palestinian struggle, as
they often say in the mainstream media,
hits a nerve on um the Arab main streets
throughout the Middle East and these
corrupt monarchies in neocolonial
regimes know that whether it's CC in
Egypt or the crown prince in Egypt. So
that their ultimate protection against
their own population is the US. So let
me ask you a more direct question then.
What does the US get out of all this?
What? I I understand the the political
desire of whoever happens to be in the
White House wanting to support Israel
for better, for worse. In my view,
mostly for worse. But what does the US
get out of all this? Why does the US
stand by and watch this genocide take
place in uh in Gaza and continue to
support the Israelis to a to a level to
an extent that just doesn't happen
anywhere else on the planet?
Well, I still think that's that's, you
know, a key question that I wish was
asked more because in the a lot of the
these discussions in the mainstream
press, it doesn't ever get to this
level, but um there's that classic State
Department memo that eventually got
declassified. I think it was from 1948
that George Kennan authored. It was I
think um State Department memo, forget
the actual number on it, but Kenan, it's
a famous state department memo in which
Kenan laid out internally the grand area
planning post World War II that that the
the regions of the world were
essentially to be in service of the US
economy.
Um and that the real threat to to that
extraction and those trade flows um
would is would would be you know
anti-colonial nationalist uh movements
and governments and of course the US
would would would use the label
communism to tar all those movements you
know whether it's Mosc and Iran and uh
Barbins in Guatemala or or Leamba in the
Congo
or I saw your program recently on on um
you know that was discussing the drug
the the Gary web and the Iran Contra and
you know of course the Senas were a mix
they weren't just purely communists but
no matter who you were it was Christians
it was radical based theology folks that
made up the FSL and government along
with some Marxists but regardless all
movements that were nationalists were
called communist and so the what The
real the I think the reason US for
decades like for decades has weaponized
the occupation of Palestine has stood
steadfast behind the Zionist project is
because what the Palestinian movement
represents and is is Arab nationalism
the struggle to have control of your own
resources your own land and that's why
it's so crucial just like they did in
removing first nation peoples when this
country is being formed with the gen the
settler colonial genocide of around 12
million people is the people for the
project the colonial project to to um
succeed you have to remove the people
from the land and so that's we see to
this day with this Abraham Accords the
so-called peace plan the an ongoing
pressure I mean Israel still controls
over half of Gaza and this ongoing
pressure to remove the Palestinians and
crush the whole notion that the Middle
East should belong to the people who
live there
>> tell us a little bit about about why
aid is not making its way to Gaza or why
aid is only entering Gaza in a trickle.
You said a minute ago that about6 of
what the Israelis have committed to is
actually making its way in. We've
already seen starvation uh in Gaza.
That's been well documented.
>> So aside from Israeli intrigence, is
there a reason why aid isn't getting
there?
Well, certainly the complicity of the US
and the uh the US and Egypt, you know,
especially,
you know, complicit in the genocide and
um so those those points like the Rafa
crossing and the points coming into
Gaza, if Egypt had had stood up and um
obviously if the US had said no, we see
that that the US really is the godfather
of this genocide. So it it really could
have never needed it could have been
stopped in a day under the Biden
administration, but Biden really
um was even more than Trump. The Biden
administration is is culpable for what
we've seen happen. Um but um but yeah, I
mean it's I think it's on that level,
John. I think it's that simple. I think
that without the complicity of the
Egyptian US governments that that the
aid would be reached. Now, the
International Court of Justice, I think
it was last week, just ruled that UNRWA,
the United Nations Relief Organization,
that's the main relief organization
operating in in Palestine, um, has to be
permitted to deliver the aid. And right
away, Mark Marco Rubio said, "Well,
we're not going to allow Renro to
function." as if the US, again, that
kind of colonial mindset, the Monroe
Doctrine mindset in Latin America being
applied to the Middle East. Um, as if
the US can dictate, you know, and just
flaunt the International Court of
Justice, which of course the US thinks
that they can, but that's where we come
in as taxpayers against genocide. I
don't know if your listeners, and I and
I don't want to, you know, take away the
the flow of the the interview.
>> No, no, go ahead. Go ahead and tell us.
Lay it out.
>> Yeah. were a grassroots movement of
thousands of taxpayers across the
country that realized that this engine
of genocide
uh could not function could the pistons
could not keep pumping if it weren't for
our money. And so really we're we're
we're complicit. in the Nerberg
principles established very clearly, you
know, after World War II when the Nazis
and Japanese war criminals are put on
trial that um ordinary people have a
duty to resist, you know, and so at a
bare minimum, what we're doing is
organizing a movement of taxpayers
um to both put our our bodies on the
line with with, you know, nonviolent
protests and arms embargo work across
the country where we're following the
leadership of groups like Palestinian
Youth Movement, but then We're also
working with the National Lawyers Guild
and the amazing attorney Heda Araf who's
one of the co-founders of the flotillaa
movement and we filed with her
leadership as the lead attorney. We
filed the only international complaint
in the world that systematically takes
the US to account for its driving role
in this genocide. And that was filed,
the most complete version of it was just
filed last uh October 7th with the
Interamerican Commission on Human
Rights, which is the the official body
in our in the Americas to uh that
adjudicates abuses by human rights
governments. It can't prosecute
unfortunately, but it's a stepping stone
towards seeking prosecution. So, we're
we're encouraging folks if you're
watching this or listening to this to to
get involved because really it's the
grassroots power and especially as our
powers taxpayers that I think there's
tremendous potential in this.
>> I want to talk about that in in more
depth uh in a moment, but you said
something that's important I want to
come back to. Um let's talk for a minute
about Egypt because you know Egypt has
kind of two faces in this conflict. On
the one hand, Egypt is not just an Arab
country. It's Umadona, right? It's the
mother of the earth in every Egyptian
school child knows that Egypt is
Umadona. And um uh Egypt has 116 million
people. Uh it's a gigantic country. U at
the same time, it was the first Arab
country to make peace with Israel, the
Camp David Accords during the Carter
presidency. And it's still a very poor
country where on the one hand the
Egyptian people, the average Egyptian on
the street wants to do something,
anything to help his Palestinian
brothers. At the same time, you you
don't want the border open because
Palestinians are going to come into
Egypt and take jobs that practically
don't exist that Egyptians could take.
Uh so the Egyptians are of two minds
over Rafa. Do they want Rafa open or do
they want Rafa closed? I think that the
Egyptian government wants it closed. And
in that respect, they're um they're
partnered with the Israelis. So, what do
you think we should expect from the
Egyptian government? And do you expect
pressure from the Egyptian people to
change the Egyptian government's policy
on Gaza?
Well, certainly
Egypt, you know, is the second largest
after Israel, the second largest
recipient of US military aid in the
world. The US has decades of sustaining
a neoc colonial regime in Egypt. you
know, uh, first and foremost with
Mubarak and then the people did rise up,
right, with the Tahar Square uprising
emblematic of that the Arab Spring.
Um, and then but then that that that
uprising uh was not completed in terms
of translating into a popular democratic
revolutionary government. Um, so instead
we we we have this new neoc colonial
regime that's quite repressive led by
General Cece. Um so under his iron rule
um we can't to answer your question we
can't expect much from the government if
you know I I heard a very strong
analysis on on this very question in an
interview that Jeremy Scill did recently
where he was um if I remember his
argument correctly and you know he's a
Jeremy Scale is a really good journalist
with Drop Site News um for your
listeners but Scale was saying that that
the government of Egypt
doesn't want to see, you know, a real
opening, whether it's of the uh the Rafa
crossing or more really what he was
saying is they don't want to see the the
Palestinian resistance succeed. But on
the other hand, it's to the benefit that
there's some ongoing conflict that the
resistance isn't completely
exterminated, but it's just subordinate
and weak because then that also
justifies Egypt's role to keep receiving
large sums of military aid from the US
and sort of be a gatekeeper, right? So
regardless of their motivations, their
actions clearly show that that they
don't when push comes to shove they
don't support the Palestinian cause.
Some um they don't um play a reliable
role and they don't they don't support
the opening that could have saved you
know who knows how many lives. um a lot
of folks on the global march to uh you
know there's a global march this last
summer to Gaza had to go to Egypt to
then try to march um into Gaza and we
had some very key tag taxpayers against
genocide leaders that went on that and
the stories they had of the level of
surveillance and repression by the
Egyptian police was was just you know
>> oh it was just it was just a couple of
years ago that media Benjamin went with
a group from Code Pink. And the
Egyptians literally broke her arm. I
mean, Medadia is a little tiny. I mean,
maybe maybe she's 90 or 95 pounds,
>> but they they physically broke her arm
>> um arresting her just because she was
trying to get to Rafa to uh escort a
shipment of of food.
>> Yeah.
>> Into into Gaza.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And that's that's a perfect
example. So this is the kind of regime
that is a pillar just like there was
like you know the sha of Iran um and you
and of course Israel and the Saudi you
know I mean here's you know how how
quickly we're asked to have amnesia
about Jamal Kosigible right like after
being uh murdered and dismembered in in
the Saudi embassy and the crown prince
clearly being involved in that now he's
he's supposedly a man of peace and we're
supposed to forget the genocide in Yemen
where the Saudi US invasion just pumped
pummeled. At one point, the UN was
saying that was the worst humanitarian
crisis in the world. But, you know, in
Orwell's landscape, these things no
longer exist. It's just the Abraham
Accords and peace.
Listen, I I spent my entire adult life
either working on the Middle East or
living in the Middle East. I was one of
the CIA's leading experts on the Middle
East. And I have just never understood
this this this regionwide dislike of
Palestinians. I spent much of my career
in the Persian Gulf, Kuwait, Saudi
Arabia, and Bahrain for the most part.
Although I spent some time in the
Emirates and in gutter as well. Um, and
I never understood why there was this
hatred for the Palestinians. I get that
Yaser Arafat backed Saddam Hussein
during the first Gulf War. But, but the
Palestinians make up the entire middle
class of these families. They are the
bankers, the professors, the lawyers,
the engineers, the teachers.
They're the ones that make these
economies run and they're Arabs and
they're mostly Muslims. So, I just don't
understand why the rest of the countries
Egypt I get it because the Egyptians are
poor and they're right on the border. I
get it. But the rest of these countries
you would think would be would beating
each other up to see who could do the
most for the Palestinian people and
they're not.
>> Yeah.
>> And they never have been.
>> What do you make of that? But that's
again where you peel away the the
curtain or you pull away the curtain and
you see who the nature of these regimes,
right? Whether it's King Hussein and
Jordan or or um you know again the sha
the the the very and and look at the
United Arab Emirates, right? That you
know that this cozy relationship they
have with the US and they get tons of
military from the US which is indirectly
completely fueling the genocide in
Sudan, right? So you know it's just like
you can look at any region of the world.
You can look at at Africa and you can
look at why isn't there more pan-African
unity against you know in the in the
postw World War II era and it's well
they come in and US and say Belgium come
in and murder Lamba and then put in
Mabu.
>> Let's let's talk about that because
you're involved you're not just involved
in in humanitarian outreach in Gaza.
Taxpayers against genocide is against
genocide no matter where it happens to
take place. So, let's let's talk about
Sudan. Um, you've got the Saudis on one
side of that fight and the Amiradis on
another side of that fight and the and
the Americans supplying arms and
material to both sides. you you've got,
you know, the the the
essentially the lynching of Muamar
Gaddafi back in what was it 2011
um at the with the support of the United
States just at a time when Gaddafi was
spending his money to develop subsaharan
African countries and to spread the
wealth in Africa. So what's the
situation now especially in the Sahel
and in subsaharan Africa in Sudan and
South Sudan with these genocides? What
can you tell us? Well, the what we can
see the the the kind of the the big
macro pattern is that the US and its
it's its subordinate European allies in
the west that have interests in you know
ongoing colonial interests like France
right in the Sahel um that that the
project of the so-called western powers
is to maintain chaos and destabilization
which even though that there's that
favorite that that famous slogan that
investment clim you know that that
companies want a stable quotequote
stable investment climate we've seen
quite well that extraction of profits
can be made in the midst of instability
what what what the west fears the most
is a unified popular uh power in in
Africa and that's exactly what's
happening right now in the Sahel where
we see more you know the you know with
countries uniting and nationalizing
their resources and saying sending the
French companies and you know getting
off the French currency and and and
whatnot define the dictates of the IMF.
So it's the similar very similar pattern
to what we what we see in the Middle
East where the US would rather uh work
through neocolonial regimes and if push
comes to shove if if there's a threat of
popular revolution or rebellion like
with the Palestinians then it would
rather rely upon violence and
destabilization to maintain power than
to see um popular democratic unity. Um
and that's clearly the case. you know
that that's also explains why the US um
hasn't um put a stop to um you know its
its involvement in the slow motion
genocide that's been happening in the
Congo um all these decades. it hasn't
you know it also shows why the US was so
hostile to the ANC you know and uh
actually collaborated and you know with
the CIA was involved in in supporting
the jailing of Mandela you know so it's
it's a again it's very similar pattern
and we it's very on display too right
now in Latin America with with the
attempts to reassert really violently
through extrajudicial killings illegal
killings of you know um the folks on
these boats outside of Venezuela
I want to ask you too about something
that Donald Trump said a week ago. He he
he said quite publicly on Truth Social
that he's considering um sending troops
to Nigeria of all places. He alleged um
this mass killing of Christians. Now
there has been well doumented attacks
against uh Christians in northern
Nigeria attributed to Boka Haram which
is a Muslim um terrorist group. There is
al-Qaeda in the Sahel that has attacked
schools and churches but there are also
Muslims being killed in large numbers in
uh Nigeria. What's the situation in
Nigeria? Are we looking at a genocide?
Does this not meet the internationally
agreed upon definition of a genocide?
And do you think that Donald Trump is
serious about sending combat troops to
Nigeria?
>> Well, I was just thinking on the last
the very last question if he's serious.
I mean, one thing we've learned in
Trump's second term is that yes, he's a
consmate grifter, but but certain things
he sends out as trial balloons or floats
out there that seem insane, he actually
has been implementing second term. So, I
don't know, but I don't think I mean,
the limited knowledge I have and I I I
need to study what's happening in
Nigeria. Um, but from what I understand,
it's not even close to a genocide. I
mean it it's actually a a gross
manipulation of the word genocide that
he's doing just like they use this idea
there was a genocide in South Africa
against white farmers. I mean yeah
there's violence and there's but this is
not what but yet then there's very real
genocides like what we see happening in
Sudan you know um just last week and and
and beyond and what we see happening in
of course in in Palestine and
interesting enough that never was
brought up. There's a slow motion
genocide happening in Haiti. It's it's
absolutely horrific. There's now over a
million and a half people have been
displaced. There are relentless murders
by what the US media calls gangs to seem
like it's not their responsibility.
There are really death squads weaponized
and working with the US. Nine times out
of 10, they're working with the US
backed regime and the US backed
oligarchy in Haiti who fund the fund
these paramilitaries.
In any event, they turn everything
upside down. So like they can take
sporadic acts of violence um that are
very real and conflate those with
genocide and yet then they're see we're
seeing industrial scale slaughter of
populations and yet they completely fund
that and weaponize that and we're seeing
systematic starvation of populations
like in Gaza or Haiti and they
completely um ignore that. So I I again
I I know I've used this word a fair
amount in this interview but it's it's
Orwellian. It's double speak. You know
what we can expect. I I don't I don't
know, you know. Um but yet the very real
involvement, what comes closer to a real
genocide in Nigeria in recent times was
what was done against the Agoni people
and when they set up the murder, the US
backed military regime there set up the
murder of Kerowi for speaking out
against how Shell and Chevron were were
destroying their land. Again, it's the
land question. And the Agoni people were
nonviolently resisting in the '9s
saying, "No, we want our land. We don't
want it to be despoiled." the the
drilling is contaminating our waters and
the USbacked military regime in Nigeria,
you know, as some folks might remember
if they went live through this um
murdered some of the key activists under
bogus trial. Now, the slaughter and the
massacre of people and of the Agoni
people and the murder of their leaders,
that's that's genocidal, but that was
again with US tax dollars.
I have a friend who um is an eminent
constitutional scholar here in
Washington. He's a former deputy
attorney general of the United States
and he represents the Keran people of uh
Myanmar. He told me recently that um
Myanmar is the only country on earth
that has been consistently at war since
the start of World War II. It's not had
one single day of peace since the
beginning of World War II. It's the only
country in the world that that is in a
situation like this. And it's all
self-imposed where there is a genocide
against the Karan people. There's a
genocide against this people and that
people and every different tribe that
might want some kind of autonomy or or
quas autonomy in uh Myanmar is at war
with the central government. Is this
something that you lose sleep over? Is
this something that you lobby the
American government about?
I haven't been involved u nor has tag at
this point been involved in this
struggle on Myammar and and Burma but
certainly one of the things that both me
personally myself personally and tag is
that as you said earlier even though the
focal point of our work is solidarity
with Palestine in this moment we do make
the connections and ultimately we're
opposed to our tax dollars being used to
fund genocide anywhere in the world and
to sustain the US empire at the expense
of humanity. You know, the 800 military
bases, the extraction of resources.
Um, we recognize like, you know, Abby
Martin just came up with this this new
documentary apparently. I'm eager to see
it, but it's it's the greatest enemy of
the earth. Something about just the
waste generated by the US military
machine and how it's destroying the
planet. But we recognize these things.
And so, um, certainly down the road, we
would like I would like to make
connections to the struggle. I know that
I've been in actions and with folks who
are part of the uh the the struggle in
Myammar here in solidarity with it,
folks in diaspora, and it's something
I'd like to learn more about and and and
make sure that we we connect we we
connect those struggles.
>> I want to ask you, circling back to the
Middle East for a minute, I want to ask
you about the situation for uh Syria's
Kurds. You know, it it it seems to me
like just as the Kurds get to a point
where they may they may win some
autonomy, let's say, or or rights within
the country where they happen to live,
be it Iraq or Turkey or Syria or Iran or
even, you know, there's a little slice
of Armenia that has a that has a sizable
Kur K Kurdish minority. uh just as they
get to the point where things look like
they may improve, they're slapped down
again.
>> And the United States more than once has
turned its backs, uh its collective
back, I should say, on the Kurdish
people, especially Iraq's Kurds. What do
you what do you see as prospects for
Syria's Kurds now that Bashar al-Assad
is long gone?
He's living in Moscow and um and Syria
has a new president supported by the
United States.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh even though he is a former member of
both al-Qaeda and ISIS. What does all
this mean for Syria's Kurds?
>> Well, it can't be good, right? Like one
thing we as you mentioned, one thing
we've learned if we study the history
honestly is that the US has no
commitment to the well-being of the
Kurdish people. And in fact, it's the
opposite. Not only did they, the US, as
you mentioned, turned its collective
back on the Kurds in the, you know, said
in the early 90s, um, with after the
first Gulf War invasion, but then the US
supported Turkey, uh, which was carrying
out a violent war of annihilation
against the Kurdish population
throughout the 90s under Bill Clinton,
right? Like, and NATO was again
weaponizing this slaughter of the
Kurdish people with our tax dollars. So
um to weaken Assad it the US was and to
gain maintain again the chaos within
Syria so that the US could come in and
and and do what it does with investments
and and military incursions and Israel
which is obviously militarily involved
in Syria. um the US supported um in a
very limited way um Kurdish autonomy,
but now that the objective of removing
Assad is is is achieved and now that we
we we have this this subservient
government in power in Syria that is
also linked, you know, that has that as
you mentioned the background of of
connections with al al-Qaeda and ISIS.
Um
I don't have any faith that the US
government will look after the
well-being or the autonomy of the
Kurdish people in Syria more than we we
already see the regime carried out a
slaughter of alawite you know Christians
and peep came out of the you know
there's no that was over a thousand plus
people killed and did the Trump
administration once mention about
Christian genocide in Syria absolutely
not
>> yeah between the the Eloise the Eloise
are well actually Bashar al-Assad was an
Alawite Muslim
and um uh the uh the Christian
community, I mean there are some
estimates that put the Christian
community uh in Syria at um at more than
5%. I I've been to Syria. I went to a to
an operating practicing Jewish synagogue
in Damascus. There's still a Jewish
community in Damascus,
>> but uh I if I were a betting man, I
would not bet money on the safety of
Christians or Jews or Alawites or any
other religious minority in Syria. Not
under this government or any other
government. For for all of his faults,
and Bashar al-Assad was a monster.
>> He was a monster. But for all of his
faults, he at least protected religious
minorities. And that's that's all out
the window now. So, Seth,
my last question for you is, well, it's
my next to the last question. What do
you what do you lose sleep over these
days? It seems like there's so much
going on around the world. Very little
of it is good. What is what bothers you
the very most?
>> I think that what what really appreciate
your questions. Um,
I think what bothers me the most is
knowing
that
that the source,
you know, of course there's many
different levels in conflicting
interests in the world that are involved
in in in in the abuses and that we've
been discussing this morning, but
there's a fundamental source coming out
of the US for for so much of the world's
strife. Like what Dr. Martin Luther King
said in ' 67, still holds during the
Riverside Church speech where he finally
he came out against the Vietnam War,
right? And he said, "The greatest
purveyor of violence in the world today
is my own government." That is as true,
if not more true today in the year 2025
as it was in ' 67. And so to see the
continuity, I'm 55, so um to see the
continuity when I was born, you know,
and my parents were involved in the
antivietnam war activism, they were
involved in civil rights movement, but
to see the continuity from the US
genocide in Vietnam to then when I was a
young adult, the first invasion of Iraq,
then the second invasion of Iraq, and so
it's like this war machine is out of
control, and it's over half our
discretionary tax budget.
And the the it's not just Trump, but
it's this bipartisan consensus that the
US is above the international law. The
US refuses to sign under the Rome
Statute to be a member of the
International Criminal Court. And now
the Trump administration's even issued
an executive order threatening people
that cooperate with the International
Criminal Court. So what I lose sleep
over what makes me what makes me want to
grind my teeth metaphorically speaking
is this impunity and knowing that uh the
source of so much of it is right here um
within the US. So but but on the flip
side it confers a responsibility and a
sense of hope that if we get better
organized the way we see um other
peoples throughout the world organizing
that we can we can have more of an
impact than we might realize. But we
have to be strategic in how we organize.
We have to be we can't just, you know,
tilt at windmills and feel like, you
know, well, I stood on a a corner again
with a sign. I mean, that's great. I'm
up for street protest, but but we have
to have a plan. We have to have
strategy. We have to actually have to
move this thing forward and envision a
world without the US empire.
>> Yeah. And uh and where can people learn
more about about you and taxpayers
against genocide and the work that
you're doing?
Um well, our website's really easy to
remember. It's just taxpayers against
genocide.org.
And um again, taxpayers against
genocide.org. And then folks can email
us. I I monitor the emails and so do
other comrades, but certainly would
would love to hear from from anybody
who's found this uh wants to get
involved. Um we are still on our
website. Uh folks will see the this the
complaint that was filed with the
Interamerican Commission on Human Rights
again with the lead attorney Huedo Roth
and other amazing attorneys with the
National Lawyers Guild who authored that
on our behalf and on behalf of
Palestinian Americans petitioning
against the US government for the murder
of their loved ones. Um so that
complaint is on the website. There's
ways how to get involved. We encourage
everybody to join. We're trying to and
we're trying to organize in regions. So
we have there's there's a tag
group that's organizing in Texas.
There's a tag group organizing in New
York. There's there's folks in Ohio.
There's of course out here in
California. So, wherever you are, you
know, again, that's the power of we need
a mass movement of taxpayers to say no.
And um not everybody can can practice
tax resistance where you just don't pay
because some people obviously if they
might have kids or they have they can't
afford to, you know, nobody wants to go
to jail or prison, but not everybody.
they just have people they depend upon.
You know that they can't do that. But
everybody can can come together as a
class of taxpayers and organize for the
accountability and the prosecution of US
officials.
There you go. Seth Donnelly, thanks so
much for joining us. Seth is the
co-founder of Taxpayers Against
Genocide. And ladies and gentlemen, as a
personal favor to me, I know I ask this
every time, but I'm going to ask it
again. Could you please uh like,
subscribe, share, tell your friends
about uh about the show? It's because of
people like you that uh we can bump that
algorithm and get out there and uh and
spread the word. So, thanks for that.
And Seth, thanks for being with us.
>> Thank you, John. Appreciate you.
>> All the best.